

TOBIAS HÖLZER

Bötzowstraße 36 10407 Berlin, Germany +49 0179 7211 240

> tobiashoelzer@hotmail.com https://tobiashoelzer.de/

ABOUT ME

I am Tobias Hölzer, a 21 years old, ongoing data scientist. I am focusing my work on climate change and hope to one day combine skills from different fields to help protect the world from climate disasters. I have already worked in many areas of IT and am particularly talented in the development and implementation of full-stack applications. I can follow a machine learning model through its entire life - from idea to research to production. You can visit my portfolio (tobiashoelzer.de) for a showcase of my past work.

EXPERIENCE

DEZ 2022 - NOW

WORKING STUDENT | IBM – CONSULTING SUSTAINABILITY

I am currently working in a project related to a big German car manufacturer and fulfil the role of a Data Engineer.

NOV 2022 - NOW

LECTURER | DHBW STUTTGART

Last November it was possible for me to gain experience as a lecturer for the first time. I held two lectures in the subject Advanced Machine Learning.

AUG 2022 - OCT 2022

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM - WEATHER COMPANY

Again, I worked on the analysis of forest-health and deforestation in Europe. This time I focussed more on scientific methods analysing the health of specific trees.

OCT 2021 - SEP 2022

DATA ENGINEER | DHBW-ENGINEERING

In my last year at the DHBW I was (am) part of the DHBW Engineering. The engineering is a student association which builds a real, electric race car and participates in Formula Student competitions worldwide. There I learned a lot about mechanical and electrical engineering. Besides my main work package, a data engineering tool, I also developed new concepts for the storage of our measurement data, did vehicle dynamics data analysis, wrote a localisation algorithm for the driverless-software and helped my comrades with everyday tasks like the production of carbon parts.

JUL 2022 – AUG 2022

TUTOR | DHBW STUTTGART

In my last year as a student at the DHBW Stuttgart I helped younger students to learn programming in Python.

FEB 2022 - APR 2022

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM - RESEARCH ZURICH

In this internship I wrote my bachelor's thesis about another climate topic: flood-detection. In this work I used computer vision to find floods on remote sensing data with the overall goal to create a larger data set for research in other fields.

AUG 2021 - NOV 2021

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM – WEATHER COMPANY

I further focussed my work on climate in this internship with the analysis of forest-health and deforestation in Europe. I worked with Big-Data Platforms like IBM Pairs and remote sensing data from the Sentinel programme.

JUN 2021 - AUG 2021

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM - RESEARCH UK

At the research team in the UK, I worked on the entity-linking-problem, a subtask of natural language processing. There I developed a Python-ML Framework based on Pytorch and proposed a new model-architecture based on the BERT language model. The model is used in a project which helps scientists fight climate change.

NOV 2020 - FEB 2021

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM – MASTER DATA MANAGEMENT

My Tasks at the MDM developer team were the configuration of CI/CD pipelines for several projects with Docker, K8s and Travis, as well as testing the new IBM Code-Engine service.

JUN 2020 - SEP 2020

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM WATSON CENTER MUNICH

At the developer team at the IBM Watson Center in Munich I developed a trustful visualization for a swarm intelligence algorithm which can predict potential water leaks in a building. Within this project I also wrote a scientific paper about trustful visualizations.

JAN 2020 - MAR 2020

INTERN / COOPERATE STUDENT | IBM DIGITAL SALES

In my first Internship at IBM, I developed a data analytics dashboard which uses the IBM Natural Language Processing Services to extract customer needs. I also maintained other NLP Projects.

EDUCATION

OCT 2022

BACHELOR OF SCIENCE | DUALE HOCHSCHULE BADEN-WÜRTTEMBERG

Cooperate Internship at IBM. In Germany it's called 'Duales Studium'. It is the main reason for my many internships at different departments at IBM. – Grade: 1.5

JUN 2019

ABITUR | HUMBOLDT GYMNASIUM BERLIN

German Highschool Graduation – Grade: 1.4 - Points: 757 of possible 900

QUALIFICATIONS

- Full-Stack Web-Development
- Docker, K8s & Cloud-Development
- Project & Architecture planning

- Computer Science
- Machine Learning & Al
- Scientific Work

PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES

- Python
- Rust
- SQL (I know it's not exactly a programming language)
- JavaScript
- TypeScript

A full list of my qualifications, languages, frameworks etc. can be found at my portfolio (tobiashoelzer.de)